[Defying the Storm]
[تحدي العاصفة]
[Episode 37]
[الحلقة 37]
Mr. Meng.
السيد منغ.
Are you okay?
هل انت بخير؟
Miss Bai.
ملكة جمال باي.
Miss Bai, Haitang is still with those Japanese.
آنسة باي ، هايتانغ لا تزال مع هؤلاء اليابانيين.
Don't worry.
لا تقلق.
This is a part of our plan.
هذا جزء من خطتنا.
Go to a safe place now.
اذهب إلى مكان آمن الآن.
Gao Lin.
جاو لين.
Take Mr. Meng to Niter Cave and protect him.
خذ السيد منغ إلى كهف نيتير وقم بحمايته.
Miss Bai, what about Haitang?
آنسة باي ، ماذا عن هايتانج؟
Don't worry.
لا تقلق.
We'll protect her.
سنحميها.
Just go.
فقط اذهب.
Be careful.
كن حذرا.
Mr. Meng, let's go.
السيد منغ ، دعنا نذهب.
Hurry up.
عجلوا.
Stop!
قف!
Okayama Shinichi.
أوكاياما شينيتشي.
Uncle Ling.
العم لينغ.
Without my endorsement,
بدون موافقتك ،
who will believe the oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding you have is real?
من سيصدق نقوش عظام الوضوء التي لديك حقيقية؟
Well.
نحن سوف.
Zeng Mu.
تسنغ مو.
When you were building this lab,
عندما كنت تبني هذا المعمل ،
in order to escape from the Japanese,
من أجل الهروب من اليابانيين ،
you built a secret room, right?
لقد بنيت غرفة سرية ، أليس كذلك؟
You cunning old man.
أيها العجوز الماكرة.
The hole I dug is finally useful now.
الحفرة التي حفرتها مفيدة أخيرًا الآن.
I dug a hole here.
لقد حفرت حفرة هنا.
Just guess,
مجرد تخمين،
where my dark room is.
أين غرفتي المظلمة.
It's in this room.
إنه في هذه الغرفة.
Guess where the hole I dug is.
خمن أين الحفرة التي حفرتها.
How could we know that?
كيف يمكننا معرفة ذلك؟
It's indeed a secret room.
إنها بالفعل غرفة سرية.
It heads directly to the underground cave.
يتجه مباشرة إلى الكهف تحت الأرض.
Great.
رائعة.
Zeng Mu.
تسنغ مو.
If so, I need to stay here.
إذا كان الأمر كذلك ، فأنا بحاجة إلى البقاء هنا.
If Haitang stays here alone,
إذا بقيت هايتانج وحدها هنا ،
I'll be worried about her.
سأكون قلقة عليها.
Uncle.
اخو الام.
Then you'll also be in danger.
إذًا ستكون أيضًا في خطر.
Girl, I know what you're thinking.
يا فتاة ، أعرف ما تفكر فيه.
But there are so many people.
لكن هناك الكثير من الناس.
If anything happens,
إذا حدث أي شيء ،
our plan would fail.
ستفشل خطتنا.
If I stay here,
إذا بقيت هنا ،
I can stop Okayama at least.
يمكنني إيقاف أوكاياما على الأقل.
I trust Zhang Qi.
أنا أثق في Zhang Qi.
I trust all of you.
أنا أثق بكم جميعا.
But please give me a chance.
لكن من فضلك أعطني فرصة.
Please let me be a part of this plan, okay?
واسمحوا لي أن أكون جزءًا من هذه الخطة ، حسنًا؟
Mr. Ling.
السيد لينغ.
Thanks to Miss Meng,
بفضل الآنسة منغ ،
X-Ray powder camera has verified
تم التحقق من كاميرا مسحوق الأشعة السينية
the cinnabar on the oracle bone
الزنجفر على عظم أوراكل
is a combination of cinnabar and hematite.
هو مزيج من الزنجفر والهيماتيت.
Do you have anything to explain, Mr. Ling?
هل لديك أي شيء لتشرحه يا سيد لينج؟
The spirit of mountains,
روح الجبال
the virtue of ancestors,
فضيلة الأسلاف ،
a beautiful antique like this.
تحفة جميلة مثل هذا.
So, Mr. Ling,
لذا ، السيد لينج ،
you also think this is the real oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding, right?
هل تعتقد أيضًا أن هذا هو نقش عظم الوحي الحقيقي لودينج ، أليس كذلك؟
But if you say it's oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding,
لكن إذا قلت إنها نقوش أوراكل العظام لودينغ ،
it's hilarious.
هذا مضحك.
Whether it's real or fake,
سواء كان ذلك حقيقيًا أو مزيفًا ،
Mr. Ling,
السيد لينغ ،
do you think you can lie to me?
هل تعتقد أنك تستطيع أن تكذب علي؟
Whether it's real or fake,
سواء كان ذلك حقيقيًا أو مزيفًا ،
I'll give you a reason.
سأعطيك سببا.
Mr. Okayama, if you don't believe it,
سيد أوكاياما ، إذا كنت لا تصدق ذلك ،
you can shoot me.
يمكنك إطلاق النار علي.
You think I don't dare to kill you?
هل تعتقد أنني لا أجرؤ على قتلك؟
Mr. Ling, you're wrong.
السيد لينج ، أنت مخطئ.
Even if I kill you now,
حتى لو قتلتك الآن
and press your fingerprint on the paper,
واضغط على بصمة إصبعك على الورقة ،
everyone will think,
الجميع سوف يفكر ،
the world-famous oracle bone inscription expert has surrendered,
استسلم خبير نقش عظام أوراكل المشهور عالميًا ،
and agreed with what I said in the article.
ووافقت على ما قلته في المقال.
What you've analyzed for a dozen of years was all wrong.
ما قمت بتحليله لعشرات السنين كان خاطئًا تمامًا.
As for Shang Dynasty,
أما بالنسبة لأسرة شانغ ،
it's a hoax.
انها خدعة.
How could you call yourself a scholar?
كيف تسمي نفسك عالم؟
It's nonsense! You shameless man!
كلام فارغ!  أنت رجل وقح!
Shameless?
وقح؟
To be honest,
صدقا،
I'm not a scholar from Tokyo Imperial University.
أنا لست باحثًا من جامعة طوكيو الإمبراطورية.
Or I can just let you see my victory.
أو يمكنني فقط السماح لك برؤية انتصاري.
Then you can die.
ثم يمكنك أن تموت.
Send a telegram.
أرسل برقية.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Uncle Ling.
العم لينغ.
I'll read it and you send it.
سوف أقرأها وترسلها.
Okay.
تمام.
Ling Wenyue, professor of history, Fuhua University,
لينغ وينيو ، أستاذ التاريخ بجامعة فوهوا ،
retrieved Study on the Yin Dynasty Calendar three years ago.
تم استرداد دراسة تقويم أسرة يين قبل ثلاث سنوات.
After three years,
بعد ثلاث سنوات ،
he admitted that he failed to compile it,
اعترف أنه فشل في تجميعها ،
and gave us the precious oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding,
وأعطانا نقوش أوراكل العظمية الثمينة لودينغ ،
which means he has given up on this study,
مما يعني أنه تخلى عن هذه الدراسة ،
and he won't study oracle bone inscriptions from now on.
ولن يدرس نقوش عظام أوراكل من الآن فصاعدًا.
Professor Ling has formally announced,
أعلن البروفيسور لينغ رسميًا ،
after studying for a dozen of years,
بعد الدراسة لعشرات السنين ،
he had a conclusion,
كان لديه استنتاج ،
Shang Dynasty has never really existed.
سلالة شانغ لم تكن موجودة حقًا.
He thinks,
يعتقد ،
whether it's Shang Dynasty or Zhou Dynasties,
سواء كانت أسرة شانغ أو سلالات تشو ،
it's not true history.
إنه ليس تاريخًا حقيقيًا.
2127 calling.
2127 يدعو.
Eta 30 minutes to target location.
إيتا 30 دقيقة للموقع المستهدف.
Commence descent to 1000 meters.
البدء بالنزول حتى 1000 متر.
Two degrees to the left.
درجتين إلى اليسار.
Xiao.
شياو.
Don't disappoint me on today's news conference.
لا تخيب ظني في المؤتمر الصحفي اليوم.
No matter what you do,
بغض النظر عن ما تفعله،
you must stop Kang Lanshan from releasing Study on the Yin Dynasty Calendar.
يجب عليك منع كانغ لانشان من إصدار دراسة حول تقويم أسرة يين.
Tell me.
أخبرني.
What do you want me to do?
ماذا تريدني ان افعل؟
Kill her.
أقتلها.
Mr. Ling has admitted,
اعترف السيد لينغ ،
China only has about two thousand years history.
الصين لديها فقط حوالي ألفي عام من التاريخ.
As for Shang and Zhou Dynasties,
أما بالنسبة لأسرتي شانغ وتشو ،
they're all legends.
كلهم أساطير.
Okayama.
أوكاياما.
With some lies and my fingerprint,
مع بعض الأكاذيب وبصمة إصبعي
you think people will believe you?
هل تعتقد أن الناس سيصدقونك؟
A repeated lie can become truth.
يمكن أن تصبح الكذبة المتكررة حقيقة.
Now that I've caught you,
الآن بعد أن مسكتك ،
I won't give you a chance to walk out of here alive and correct it.
لن أعطيك فرصة للخروج من هنا حياً وتصحيح الأمر.
Continue.
يكمل.
Okayama.
أوكاياما.
If I can prove oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding doesn't originate from Kingdom Wu Ding,
إذا كان بإمكاني إثبات أن نقوش أوراكل العظمية لودينغ لم تنشأ من Kingdom Wu Ding ،
what will you do?
ماذا ستفعل؟
Wait a second.
انتظر لحظة.
Mr. Okayama.
السيد أوكاياما.
Since we've got oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding,
منذ أن حصلنا على نقوش عظمية أوراكل لودينغ ،
you can kill them now.
يمكنك قتلهم الآن.
Don't say too much.
لا تقل كثيرا.
Just do it.
افعل ذلك.
We have something more important to do.
لدينا شيء أكثر أهمية للقيام به.
Calm down, Mr. Ando.
اهدأ يا سيد أندو.
Ling Wenyue is right.
لينغ وينيو محق.
If he can prove it himself,
إذا استطاع إثبات ذلك بنفسه ،
and we can record it and take a photo,
ويمكننا تسجيله والتقاط صورة ،
it's more persuasive than the article I wrote.
إنه أكثر إقناعًا من المقال الذي كتبته.
Besides, we are in the mountain,
الى جانب ذلك ، نحن في الجبل ،
where can they go?
اين يمكن ان يذهبوا
56th Division will arrive at Hongshi half an hour later.
ستصل الفرقة 56 إلى Hongshi بعد نصف ساعة.
Everything is in our control now.
كل شيء تحت سيطرتنا الآن.
All scholars can't do great things.
لا يستطيع جميع العلماء فعل أشياء عظيمة.
Take the troop to the side way with the main force.
خذ القوات إلى الطريق الجانبي مع القوة الرئيسية.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Play it by ear.
لعبها بالاذن.
Hong'en.
هونغ إن.
Qianying.
Qianying.
Help me greet them.
ساعدني في الترحيب بهم.
Okay.
تمام.
I'll talk with him.
سأتحدث معه.
Okay, just go.
حسنًا ، اذهب فقط.
Hong'en.
هونغ إن.
Didn't you go to western Yunnan with Uncle Meng?
ألم تذهب إلى غرب يونان مع العم منغ؟
They're fine?
انهم بخير؟
Where are my dad and Haitang?
أين أبي وهايتانغ؟
I escaped from there.
هربت من هناك.
Your dad is still with them.
والدك لا يزال معهم.
But what do you mean by your dad and Haitang?
لكن ماذا تقصد بوالدك وهايتانج؟
They went to western Yunnan to save Uncle Meng,
ذهبوا إلى غرب يونان لإنقاذ العم منغ ،
as well as Zhenzhu.
وكذلك Zhenzhu.
What? Zhenzhu also went there?
ماذا؟  Zhenzhu أيضا ذهب هناك؟
Why did she go there?
لماذا ذهبت هناك؟
She said she has government resources.
قالت أن لديها موارد حكومية.
She can help to save Uncle Meng if necessary.
يمكنها المساعدة في إنقاذ العم منغ إذا لزم الأمر.
Well, Hong'en.
حسنًا ، Hong'en.
Before Zhenzhu left,
قبل مغادرة Zhenzhu ،
she asked me to deliver this letter to you.
طلبت مني تسليم هذه الرسالة لك.
Qianying.
Qianying.
Qianying, come here.
Qianying ، تعال هنا.
Please excuse me for a while.
يرجى المعذرة لبعض الوقت.
Xiao Hong'en is unreliable.
شياو هونغ آن لا يمكن الاعتماد عليها.
We need to have a plan b.
نحن بحاجة إلى خطة ب.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Men have their dignity, so does newspaper,
للرجال كرامتهم وكذلك الصحف ،
and so does a nation.
وكذلك الأمة.
Without these dignities,
بدون هذه الكرامات ،
men will no long exist, so will newspaper,
لن يبقى الرجال طويلاً ، وكذلك الصحف ،
and so will a nation.
وكذلك الأمة.
If I can die for the newspaper,
إذا كان بإمكاني الموت من أجل الصحيفة ،
it would be my glory.
سيكون مجدي.
Hong'en.
هونغ إن.
After I went there,
بعد أن ذهبت إلى هناك ،
whether I will live or die,
سواء كنت سأعيش أو أموت ،
it all depends on you.
كل هذا يتوقف على لك.
You're the one
انت المختار
to decide whether I'll live or die.
لتقرير ما إذا كنت سأعيش أو أموت.
So this is what you mean.
لذلك هذا ما تعنيه.
The bomber checked the bomb device again.
قام المفجر بفحص العبوة مرة أخرى.
Copy that.
انسخ هذا.
Check the bomb device.
افحص العبوة القنبلة.
Ms. Kang.
آنسة.  كانغ.
Hong'en.
هونغ إن.
You work for Director Lu, right?
أنت تعمل مع المخرج لو ، أليس كذلك؟
You're finally here.
أنت هنا أخيرًا.
Where is Kang Lanshan?
أين كانغ لانشان؟
They said,
قالوا ،
they would change a place to release it.
سوف يغيرون مكانًا لإطلاقه.
Bai Fei took many people to protect them.
أخذ باي فاي الكثير من الناس لحمايتهم.
I can't defeat them.
لا أستطيع هزيمتهم.
Fortunately,
لحسن الحظ،
you're finally here.
أنت هنا أخيرًا.
Well,
نحن سوف،
they went to the Democratic Wall.
ذهبوا إلى الجدار الديمقراطي.
Come on, let's check there.
تعال ، دعنا نتحقق هناك.
Hurry up.
عجلوا.
Ms. Kang.
آنسة.  كانغ.
I need you to act a play with me.
أحتاجك لتمثيل مسرحية معي.
Do you trust me?
هل تثق بي؟
Yes.
نعم.
Okay, Qianying,
حسنًا ، Qianying ،
go to Shundecheng Printing House now,
اذهب إلى Shundecheng Printing House الآن ،
and ask for the extra of Xinzhi Times a month ago.
واطلب المزيد من Xinzhi Times قبل شهر.
Extra?
إضافي؟
I know.
أنا أعرف.
Qianying, go there right now.
Qianying ، اذهب هناك الآن.
Just go.
فقط اذهب.
Okay.
تمام.
Ms. Kang.
آنسة.  كانغ.
Thank you.
شكرًا لك.
On behalf of Professor Ling Wenyue from the Department of History, Fuhua University,
بالنيابة عن البروفيسور لينغ وينيو من قسم التاريخ بجامعة فوهوا ،
I'm here to release his study,
أنا هنا لأطلق دراسته ،
Study on the Yin Dynasty Calendar.
دراسة عن تقويم أسرة يين.
In 1930,
في عام 1930 ،
Professor Jin Zhilie and Ling Wenyue from the Department of History, Fuhua University,
البروفيسور Jin Zhilie و Ling Wenyue من قسم التاريخ ، جامعة Fuhua ،
found an oracle bone inscription in Xiaotun, Anyang.
العثور على نقش أوراكل العظمي في شياوتون ، أنيانغ.
Mr. Ling, tell me.
السيد لينج ، أخبرني.
Record it.
سجله.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Do you still remember the day when you went to the news conference?
هل ما زلت تتذكر اليوم الذي ذهبت فيه إلى المؤتمر الصحفي؟
You raised a question.
لقد طرحت سؤالا.
Mr. Ling.
السيد لينغ.
Let me ask you one more question.
دعني أطرح عليك سؤالاً آخر.
Why is the record of a meteor shower carved,
لماذا تم نحت سجل زخات الشهب ،
instead of inscription?
بدلا من النقش؟
Why is the record of a meteor shower on oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding carved
لماذا تم نحت سجل زخات الشهب على نقوش عظمية أوراكل لودينج
Your question gave me much inspiration.
سؤالك أعطاني الكثير من الإلهام.
There are three cinnabar carvings behind it.
يوجد خلفه ثلاث منحوتات من الزنجفر.
Professor Ling translated it as the record of a meteor shower.
ترجمها البروفيسور لينغ على أنها سجل لزخ نيزك.
The westward movement of stars.
حركة النجوم باتجاه الغرب.
In all these years,
في كل هذه السنوات ،
we thought this is a meteor shower
كنا نظن أن هذا نيزك
that happened when King Wu Ding first established his kingdom,
حدث ذلك عندما أسس الملك وو دينغ مملكته لأول مرة ،
so we thought this oracle bone originated from Shang Dynasty when King Wu Ding was in charge.
لذلك اعتقدنا أن عظمة أوراكل نشأت من أسرة شانغ عندما كان الملك وو دينغ مسؤولاً.
[Xinzhi Times Office]
[Xinzhi Times Office]
Yes, Zhou.
نعم تشو.
I'll read it and you copy it.
سوف أقرأها وأنت تقوم بنسخها.
And then send it to
ثم أرسلها إلى
The New York Times,
اوقات نيويورك،
The Washington Post,
واشنطن بوست
The Times,
الأوقات،
France Soir and Pravda.
فرنسا سوار وبرافدا.
I rewrote Study on the Yin Dynasty Calendar in three years,
أعدت كتابة دراسة عن تقويم أسرة يين في ثلاث سنوات ،
and found many literary forms that contain the record of a meteor shower.
ووجدت العديد من الأشكال الأدبية التي تحتوي على سجل زخات الشهب.
So,
لذا،
the practice of divination that people commonly accept may not be right.
قد لا تكون ممارسة العرافة التي يقبلها الناس عمومًا صحيحة.
The rubbings in the Department of History in Fuhua are not enough.
الاحتكاكات في قسم التاريخ في فوهوا ليست كافية.
What should we do if it's not here?
ماذا يجب أن نفعل إذا لم يكن هنا؟
So,
لذا،
your mom went to Chongqing.
والدتك ذهبت إلى تشونغتشينغ.
I've applied to the Nanjing Institute.
لقد تقدمت بطلب إلى معهد نانجينغ.
We'll copy all the rubbings of oracle bones and bronze wares there.
سنقوم بنسخ جميع فرك عظام أوراكل والأواني البرونزية هناك.
I found it.
لقد وجدتها.
The conclusion is,
الاستنتاج هو ،
the meaning of the record of a meteor shower is the westward movement of stars.
معنى سجل زخات الشهب هو حركة النجوم باتجاه الغرب.
But this oracle bone inscription of Wuding doesn't originate from Kingdom Wu Ding.
لكن هذا النقش العظمي الوحي لودينغ لم ينشأ من Kingdom Wu Ding.
But the westward movement of stars,
لكن حركة النجوم باتجاه الغرب ،
wasn't a meteor shower that happened in Kingdom Wu Ding,
لم يكن زخة نيزك حدثت في مملكة وو دينغ ،
which didn't match the idea that Professor Ling previously believed.
التي لا تتطابق مع الفكرة التي اعتقدها البروفيسور لينغ سابقًا.
On the contrary, it records one of the great migrations of human civilization.
على العكس من ذلك ، فهو يسجل إحدى الهجرات العظيمة للحضارة الإنسانية.
After the chaos in Shang Dynasty,
بعد الفوضى في عهد أسرة شانغ ،
Kingdom Shang met a huge calamity.
واجهت مملكة شانغ كارثة ضخمة.
There were floods and turmoils in politics.
كانت هناك فيضانات واضطرابات في السياسة.
People suffered a lot,
عانى الناس كثيرا ،
so Pan Geng decided to relocate the capital.
لذلك قرر بان جينج نقل العاصمة.
This was recorded in The Book of History, Pan Geng.
تم تسجيل ذلك في كتاب التاريخ ، بان جينج.
There was a huge calamity.
كانت هناك كارثة كبيرة.
The former Emperor didn't stay in the capital.
لم يبق الإمبراطور السابق في العاصمة.
He chose to move capital for people's interest instead.
اختار نقل رأس المال لمصلحة الناس بدلاً من ذلك.
It means,
هذا يعني،
King Pan Geng didn't stay in the former capital.
لم يبق الملك بان جينج في العاصمة السابقة.
For the interest of people,
من أجل مصلحة الناس ،
he decided to relocate the capital.
قرر نقل العاصمة.
In order to get out of trouble and restore people's livelihood,
من أجل الخروج من المأزق وإعادة الحياة للناس ،
King Pan Geng defeated much opposition,
هزم الملك بان جينج الكثير من المعارضة ،
and moved the capital from Yan, Qufu of Shandong now,
ونقلوا العاصمة من يان وتشوفو من شاندونغ الآن ،
to Yin, Xiaotun of Anyang now.
إلى Yin ، Xiaotun من Anyang الآن.
This great migration from east to west is known as the westward movement of stars.
تُعرف هذه الهجرة العظيمة من الشرق إلى الغرب بحركة النجوم باتجاه الغرب.
Because of this migration,
بسبب هذه الهجرة ،
Shang Dynasty survived the floods,
نجت أسرة شانغ من الفيضانات ،
and the chaos in politics,
والفوضى في السياسة ،
which stabilized the central power,
مما أدى إلى استقرار القوة المركزية ،
and laid a solid foundation for the prosperous of Kingdom Wu Ding.
وأرسى أساسًا متينًا لازدهار مملكة وو دينغ.
Thus the decaying Shang Dynasty became prosperous again.
وهكذا أصبحت أسرة شانغ المتدهورة مزدهرة مرة أخرى.
On this oracle bone,
على عظم أوراكل هذا ،
look at its front.
انظر إلى مقدمته.
The writing on this oracle bone belongs to two kingdoms.
الكتابة على عظم أوراكل هذه تنتمي إلى مملكتين.
One part of it originated from Kingdom Wu Ding,
جزء منها نشأ من Kingdom Wu Ding ،
and the other part belongs to Kingdom Pan Geng that was a hundred years earlier.
والجزء الآخر ينتمي إلى Kingdom Pan Geng التي كانت قبل مائة عام.
In order to relocate the capital, Pan Geng practiced divination three times.
من أجل نقل العاصمة ، مارس بان جينج العرافة ثلاث مرات.
The first and second times were inauspiciousness.
المرة الأولى والثانية كانت الشؤم.
But King Pan Geng insisted to have the third divination,
لكن الملك بان جينج أصر على أن يكون لديه العرافة الثالثة ،
and the conclusion was great auspiciousness,
وكانت النتيجة مباركة عظيمة ،
so Pan Geng decided to relocate the capital.
لذلك قرر بان جينج نقل العاصمة.
Combined with three articles in The Book of History, Pan Geng,
مدمجًا مع ثلاثة مقالات في كتاب التاريخ ، بان جينج ،
we had a second argument,
كان لدينا حجة ثانية ،
to prove the relocation of capital is a historical fact.
إثبات نقل رأس المال حقيقة تاريخية.
This was previously called oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding.
كان هذا يسمى سابقا بنقوش أوراكل العظمي لودينج.
Also, the historians and archaeologists
وكذلك المؤرخون وعلماء الآثار
have discovered thousands of oracle bone inscriptions.
اكتشفوا الآلاف من نقوش عظام أوراكل.
They confirmed oracle bone inscriptions
أكدوا نقوش عظام أوراكل
are the earliest mature writing system discovered in China so far.
هي أقدم نظام كتابة مكتمل تم اكتشافه في الصين حتى الآن.
It is not only the origin of Chinese characters,
ليس فقط أصل الأحرف الصينية ،
but also the beginning of Chinese history.
ولكن أيضًا بداية التاريخ الصيني.
About the other part, in Kingdom Wu Ding,
حول الجزء الآخر ، في Kingdom Wu Ding ،
King Wu Ding also practiced divination three times.
كما مارس الملك وو دينغ العرافة ثلاث مرات.
He asked God,
سأل الله:
whether to fight against Qiang Region that has been harassing Shang.
سواء للقتال ضد منطقة Qiang التي كانت تضايق Shang.
The first and second times were inauspiciousness.
المرة الأولى والثانية كانت الشؤم.
The third time was auspiciousness,
كانت المرة الثالثة الميمونة ،
so Zi, the wife of King Wu Ding,
لذا زي ، زوجة الملك وو دينغ ،
took a troop and defeated them.
تولى القوات وهزمهم.
She gained a peaceful environment for Shang.
اكتسبت بيئة سلمية لشانغ.
This war was also recorded in The Book of Zuo Zhuan and Records of the Historian.
تم تسجيل هذه الحرب أيضًا في كتاب Zuo Zhuan وسجلات المؤرخ.
We had a second argument,
كان لدينا حجة ثانية ،
and the conclusion is,
والاستنتاج هو
this war is a historical fact.
هذه الحرب حقيقة تاريخية.
King Pan Geng was in charge for 28 years,
كان الملك بان جينج في السلطة لمدة 28 عامًا ،
during 1398 BC to 1371 BC.
خلال الفترة من 1398 إلى 1371 قبل الميلاد.
Then King Xiaoxin was in charge for 21 years,
ثم كان الملك شياوكسين في السلطة لمدة 21 عامًا ،
King Xiaoyi was in charge for ten years.
كان الملك شياويي في السلطة لمدة عشر سنوات.
Then it was King Wu Ding,
ثم كان الملك وو دينغ ،
who was in charge for 59 years.
الذي كان مسؤولا لمدة 59 عاما.
There are twelve Kings in Shang Dynasty.
هناك اثنا عشر ملكًا في عهد أسرة شانغ.
The total time is 287 years.
الوقت الإجمالي 287 سنة.
Besides,
بجانب،
Pan Geng relocated capital in 1350 BC.
نقل بان جينج العاصمة في عام 1350 قبل الميلاد.
Jifa defeated the King of Shang in 1075 BC.
هزمت جيفا ملك شانغ عام 1075 قبل الميلاد.
The oracle bone inscriptions can match with
يمكن أن تتطابق نقوش عظام أوراكل مع
Records of the Historian, Yinben,
سجلات المؤرخ ، ينبن ،
Bamboo Annals,
حوليات الخيزران
The Book of History.
كتاب التاريخ.
The antiques are mutually confirmed with historical records.
تم تأكيد التحف بشكل متبادل مع السجلات التاريخية.
This can prove that Shang Dynasty really exists.
هذا يمكن أن يثبت أن أسرة شانغ موجودة بالفعل.
Lying! You are lying!
يكذب!  انت تكذب!
You can doubt the history.
يمكنك الشك في التاريخ.
Mencius once said,
قال منسيوس ذات مرة ،
better no book rather than trust book completely.
من الأفضل عدم وجود كتاب بدلاً من الثقة في الكتاب تمامًا.
So as scholars studying history,
فكما يدرس العلماء التاريخ ،
we should hold the attitude
يجب أن نتحمل الموقف
to be loyal to history and empirical evidence,
لتكون مخلصًا للتاريخ والأدلة التجريبية ،
to spread faith or doubt as you believe.
لنشر الإيمان أو الشك كما تعتقد.
On this oracle bone,
على عظم أوراكل هذا ،
it is the writing of our nation,
إنها كتابة أمتنا ،
the culture of our nation,
ثقافة أمتنا ،
and the wisdom of our ancestors.
وحكمة اسلافنا.
You can't deny it with your lies!
لا يمكنك إنكارها بأكاذيبك!
Chinese writing is the only language in the world that has never stopped developing up to now.
الكتابة الصينية هي اللغة الوحيدة في العالم التي لم تتوقف عن التطور حتى الآن.
It not only records the history of China,
إنه لا يسجل فقط تاريخ الصين ،
but also it is the most important spiritual bond that makes China.
لكنها أيضًا أهم رباط روحي يصنع الصين.
The words that have been passed on from these broken books,
الكلمات التي تم تناقلها من هذه الكتب المكسورة ،
the inheritance that hasn't been interrupted for thousands of years,
الميراث الذي لم ينقطع منذ آلاف السنين ،
and the culture that is embedded in our soil and our blood,
والثقافة المتأصلة في ترابنا ودمائنا ،
they are the reputation of our ancestors,
هم سمعة أسلافنا ،
the inheritance of our nation.
ميراث أمتنا.
Xinzhi Times!
Xinzhi تايمز!
Extra! Extra!
إضافي!  إضافي!
Extra!
إضافي!
Have a look!
الق نظرة!
Come and have a look!
يأتي وننظر لها!
Panlong Society of Japan wanted to falsify the beginning of Chinese history.
أرادت جمعية بانلونج اليابانية تزوير بداية التاريخ الصيني.
Their conspiracy has exposed.
لقد كشفت مؤامراتهم.
Please have a look.
ألق نظرة من فضلك.
In 1920,
في عام 1920 ،
Okayama Shinichi from Panlong Society of Japan stole oracle bones from Yin Dynasty ruins.
سرق أوكاياما شينيتشي من جمعية بانلونج اليابانية عظام أوراكل من أنقاض أسرة يين.
From 1929 to 1941,
من عام 1929 إلى عام 1941 ،
he smuggled many antiques in Anyang out of China.
قام بتهريب العديد من التحف في أنيانغ خارج الصين.
In 1939,
في عام 1939 ،
the Japanese wanted to steal Simuwu Cauldron,
أراد اليابانيون سرقة Simuwu Cauldron ،
but they failed.
لكنهم فشلوا.
From 1942 to 1943,
من عام 1942 إلى عام 1943 ،
Japanese troops stationed in Henan
القوات اليابانية المتمركزة في خنان
took advantage of local bandits
استفاد من قطاع الطرق المحليين
to rob many cultural relics from Yin Dynasty ruins.
لسرقة العديد من الآثار الثقافية من أطلال أسرة يين.
Then they transported the relics to Japan through the port of Dalian Far East Refinery.
ثم نقلوا الآثار إلى اليابان عبر ميناء مصفاة داليان في الشرق الأقصى.
Whether it's oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding or Pan Geng,
سواء كانت نقوش عظمية أوراكل لودينج أو بان جينج ،
now I have it.
الآن لدي ذلك.
As for you,
أما أنت
I won't let you walk out of here alive.
لن أسمح لك بالخروج من هنا حيا.
Send a telegram.
أرسل برقية.
Yes, sir.
نعم سيدي.
Based on previous messages,
بناءً على الرسائل السابقة ،
Comrade Xu Zhice will lead the enemies to the lab
سيقود الرفيق Xu Zhice الأعداء إلى المختبر
before 4 o'clock this afternoon.
قبل الساعة الرابعة بعد ظهر اليوم.
Luckily, Zhenzhu made a plan.
لحسن الحظ ، وضع Zhenzhu خطة.
And when we were in Kunming,
وعندما كنا في كونمينغ ،
she has told me the time and schedule.
لقد أخبرتني بالوقت والجدول الزمني.
Before we left Fuhua University,
قبل مغادرتنا جامعة فوهوا ،
I've had a deal with Ms. Kang.
لقد أبرمت صفقة مع السيدة كانغ.
When Mr. Ling meets Okayama today,
عندما يلتقي السيد لينغ مع أوكاياما اليوم ،
they will release Study on the Yin Dynasty Calendar at an appropriate time.
سيصدرون دراسة حول تقويم أسرة يين في الوقت المناسب.
They can't release it too early.
لا يمكنهم إطلاقه في وقت مبكر جدًا.
Or we will be in danger.
أو سنكون في خطر.
And they can't release it too late.
ولا يمكنهم الإفراج عنه بعد فوات الأوان.
If they release it after Okayama's article,
إذا أطلقوا سراحه بعد مقال أوكاياما ،
all our previous efforts will be wasted.
كل جهودنا السابقة ستضيع.
So, Ms. Kang will release it at 6 o'clock on the date of 21st.
لذا ، ستطلقه السيدة كانغ في تمام الساعة 6 من يوم 21.
Haitang told Lanshan and me this plan.
أخبرني هايتانغ Lanshan وأنا بهذه الخطة.
It's like besieging Wei to rescue Zhao.
إنه مثل محاصرة وي لإنقاذ تشاو.
So now,
و الآن،
I'll calm down,
سأهدأ ،
and play this empty city tactic with you.
ولعب هذا التكتيك الفارغ معك.
The so-called Chinese civilization is the accumulation of falsity.
إن ما يسمى بالحضارة الصينية هو تراكم الكذب.
China is a rootless duckweed.
الصين طحلب بط لا جذور له.
Historians represented by Ling Wenyue,
المؤرخون الذين يمثلهم لينغ وينيو ،
denied their studies totally.
نفوا دراستهم تماما.
It also proved,
ثبت أيضًا ،
even the best scholars of China have lost faith in its history.
حتى أفضل علماء الصين فقدوا الثقة في تاريخها.
It is willing to cede China's political,
إنها مستعدة للتنازل عن السياسة الصينية ،
cultural and economic management rights to Japan, which is superior.
حقوق الإدارة الثقافية والاقتصادية لليابان متفوقة.
There is no truth in the world!
لا توجد حقيقة في العالم!
There are only power and weakness.
لا يوجد سوى القوة والضعف.
I own the right of speech.
أنا أملك حق الكلام.
The words I said repeatedly are the truth!
الكلمات التي قلتها مرارا هي الحقيقة!
History,
تاريخ،
is written by the powerful people.
كتبه أصحاب النفوذ.
Post this article now!
أضف هذا المقال الآن!
Where is the beginning of Chinese history?
أين هي بداية التاريخ الصيني؟
Oracle bone inscriptions are
نقوش أوراكل العظام
the earliest mature writing system discovered in China so far.
أقدم نظام كتابة مكتمل تم اكتشافه في الصين حتى الآن.
It is not only the origin of Chinese characters,
ليس فقط أصل الأحرف الصينية ،
but also the beginning of Chinese civilization.
ولكن أيضًا بداية الحضارة الصينية.
Okay, Zhou, that's it.
حسنًا ، تشو ، هذا كل شيء.
Post it now.
انشرها الآن.
Zhou, wait a second.
تشو ، انتظر ثانية.
He is upstairs!
هو في الطابق العلوي!
Hello, Zhou.
مرحبا تشو.
There is one more message, post it together.
هناك رسالة أخرى ، انشرها معًا.
Just copy it.
فقط انسخه.
Panlong Society of Japan bought oil fields in Jing'an secretly,
اشترت جمعية Panlong اليابانية حقول النفط في جينجان سراً ،
and they asked Lu Ziyi from Kuomintang,
وسألوا Lu Ziyi من Kuomintang ،
Political Discipline Department,
قسم الانضباط السياسي
Air Force Officer School,
مدرسة ضباط القوات الجوية ،
Central Aviation Council to manage it.
مجلس الطيران المركزي لإدارتها.
They made a huge profit by supplying inferior fuel to our domestic wars.
لقد حققوا أرباحًا ضخمة من خلال توفير وقود أقل جودة لحروبنا الداخلية.
It not only greatly damaged our military capabilities,
لم يضر فقط بقدراتنا العسكرية بشكل كبير ،
but also directly led to dozens of aircraft accidents, including the 428 air battle.
لكنها أدت أيضًا بشكل مباشر إلى عشرات حوادث الطائرات ، بما في ذلك 428 معركة جوية.
A virtuous man needs to think of nine things,
يحتاج الرجل الفاضل إلى التفكير في تسعة أشياء ،
to be insightful, to listen carefully,
أن تكون ثاقبًا ، وأن تصغي جيدًا ،
to be gentle, to be polite,
أن تكون لطيفًا ، وأن تكون مؤدبًا ،
to be faithful, to be steady,
أن تكون مخلصًا ، أن تكون ثابتًا ،
to be thoughtful, to be calm,
أن تكون مدروسًا ، وأن تكون هادئًا ،
and to be righteous.
ولكي أكون صالحاً.
Hong'en, well done.
Hong'en ، أحسنت.
Do you know what it means?
هل تعرف ماذا يعني ذلك؟
It means,
هذا يعني،
we need to be reasonable,
يجب أن نكون عقلانيين ،
and introspect ourselves from time to time.
ونتأمل أنفسنا من وقت لآخر.
People will make mistakes,
سيرتكب الناس أخطاء ،
but they can't just let it be.
لكنهم لا يستطيعون السماح لها بذلك.
So, uncle,
لذا ، عمي ،
if I made a mistake and correct it,
إذا أخطأت وصححتها ،
I'm still a good person, right?
ما زلت شخصًا جيدًا ، أليس كذلك؟
What do you think?
ماذا تعتقد؟
This is not the man I know.
هذا ليس الرجل الذي أعرفه.
This is not Xiao Hong'en.
هذا ليس شياو هونغ إن.
You asked me if I loved you.
سألتني إذا كنت أحببتك.
Yes.
نعم.
But I love the Xiao Hong'en that always tells me
لكني أحب Xiao Hong'en الذي يخبرني دائمًا
to be patriotic,
أن تكون وطنيًا ،
to never surrender,
لا تستسلم أبدا ،
to never be insulted.
حتى لا تتعرض للإهانة.
I'm coming.
أنا قادم.
Come on.
هيا.
Sir.
سيد.
What?
ماذا؟
It's six o'clock, come on.
إنها السادسة ، هيا.
B-25.
ب -25.
It's B-25.
إنه B-25.
Where is it?
أين هي؟
Combat aircraft of Wujiaba is here.
هنا الطائرات المقاتلة من Wujiaba.
I can only hear it.
أستطيع فقط سماعه.
Wujiaba wants to kill all enemies here.
Wujiaba يريد قتل كل الأعداء هنا.
The B-25 is a medium bomber.
القاذفة B-25 هي قاذفة متوسطة.
The maximum payload is 1361 kilograms.
الحمولة القصوى 1361 كجم.
If it drops bombs here,
إذا أسقطت قنابل هنا ،
the lab and cave will all be destroyed.
سيتم تدمير المختبر والكهف.
No one can escape.
لا أحد يستطيع الهروب.
What can we do now?
ماذا نستطيع ان نفعل الآن؟
We need to stop it.
نحن بحاجة إلى إيقافه.
But we don't have communication equipments.
لكن ليس لدينا معدات اتصال.
How can we...
كيف يمكننا ...
That's it?
هذا هو؟
The B-25 has a disadvantage.
و B-25 له عيب.
It takes a long way to get into the attack line.
يستغرق الوصول إلى خط الهجوم شوطًا طويلاً.
Sir, refuel Xishan immediately.
سيدي ، تزود بالوقود Xishan على الفور.
Can you make it fly?
هل يمكنك جعلها تطير؟
Of course it can.
بالطبع يمكن ذلك.
Come on.
هيا.
Nianqiao, what happened?
Nianqiao ، ماذا حدث؟
The Captain gave me a signal.
أعطاني الكابتن إشارة.
We need to stop the bomber from dropping bombs.
نحن بحاجة إلى منع الانتحاري من إلقاء القنابل.
2127 calling.
2127 يدعو.
2127 approaching target location.
2127 يقترب من الموقع المستهدف.
Control tower, control tower.
برج المراقبة ، برج المراقبة.
Radio is out of order.
الراديو معطل.
There is strong magnetic interference nearby.
يوجد تداخل مغناطيسي قوي في الجوار.
Descend to 500 meters.
النزول إلى 500 متر.
Copy that.
انسخ هذا.
Xishan requesting liftoff.
شيشان يطلب الإقلاع.
It can fly for about fifteen minutes.
يمكن أن تطير لمدة خمس عشرة دقيقة.
Go ahead.
إنطلق.
Be careful.
كن حذرا.
Sir.
سيد.
We just got an important message.
لقد تلقينا للتو رسالة مهمة.
What important message?
ما هي الرسالة المهمة؟
Nothing is more important than releasing oracle bone inscriptions of Wuding to the world!
لا شيء أهم من إطلاق نقوش عظام الوضوء للعالم!
Mr. Okayama.
السيد أوكاياما.
It's five past six now.
إنها السادسة وخمس دقائق الآن.
We must gather with the main force at Hongshi Road before seven o'clock.
يجب أن نجتمع مع القوة الرئيسية في طريق Hongshi قبل الساعة السابعة صباحًا.
Just deal with the mess here.
فقط تعامل مع الفوضى هنا.
I'll read the telegram to you.
سأقرأ لك البرقية.
Haitang, Mr. Ling.
هايتانج ، السيد لينج.
Because it takes some time to get the fuel,
لأن الحصول على الوقود يستغرق بعض الوقت ،
I'll refuel the aircraft at about six o'clock.
سأقوم بإعادة تزويد الطائرة بالوقود في حوالي الساعة السادسة.
At ten past six,
في السادسة وعشر دقائق ،
I'll drive the plane,
سأقود الطائرة ،
and warn with a hovering roar,
وتحذر بزئير يحوم ،
to attract the indoor enemies' attention.
لجذب انتباه الأعداء الداخليين.
The enemies will be distracted for about two minutes.
سيتم تشتيت الأعداء لمدة دقيقتين تقريبًا.
In two minutes,
في دقيقتين ،
Donglai, Zhenzhu,
Donglai ، Zhenzhu ،
try to let the indoor enemies go outside.
حاول السماح للأعداء الداخليين بالخروج.
Then I'll fly away and drop bombs at a proper time.
ثم سأطير بعيدًا وألقي بالقنابل في الوقت المناسب.
Mr. Zeng.
السيد تسنغ.
Find the certain place to hide.
ابحث عن مكان معين للاختباء.
Nianqiao, take Mr. Meng to the safe place we arranged.
Nianqiao ، اصطحب السيد Meng إلى المكان الآمن الذي رتبناه.
Haitang, Mr. Ling.
هايتانج ، السيد لينج.
Go to the underground cave immediately,
اذهب إلى الكهف تحت الأرض على الفور ،
remember?
تذكر؟
So you all know the safe places for you to hide.
حتى تعرف جميعًا الأماكن الآمنة للاختباء فيها.
Please repeat it to me.
من فضلك كررها لي.
Wait.
انتظر.
I have a question.
عندي سؤال.
Mr. Ling and Haitang won't face Sima Yi.
لن يواجه السيد لينغ وهايتانغ سيما يي.
They are going to face the lunatic Okayama Shinichi,
سوف يواجهون المجنون أوكاياما شينيتشي ،
and the well-trained flying squad of Japanese 56th Division.
وفرقة الطيران المدربة تدريباً جيداً من الفرقة 56 اليابانية.
You said you'll drop bombs according to time.
قلت إنك ستسقط القنابل حسب الوقت.
How do you know Mr. Ling and Haitang
كيف تعرف السيد لينغ وهايتانغ
have entered the underground cave or the safe place?
دخلت الكهف تحت الأرض أم المكان الآمن؟
If they are still outside,
إذا كانوا لا يزالون بالخارج ،
instead of entering the safe place,
بدلاً من دخول المكان الآمن ،
will you still drop the bombs?
هل ستستمر في إلقاء القنابل؟
Well, I think, the interests of the whole are more important.
حسنًا ، أعتقد أن مصالح الكل أكثر أهمية.
It wouldn't be a pity if I die.
لن يكون من المؤسف أن أموت.
Uncle Ling is right.
العم لينغ على حق.
Zhang Qi.
تشانغ تشى.
Drop the bombs according to time.
أسقط القنابل حسب الوقت.
At six o'clock this afternoon,
في الساعة السادسة بعد ظهر اليوم ،
BBC released a piece of news.
أصدرت بي بي سي قطعة من الأخبار.
Fuhua University announced to the world,
أعلنت جامعة فوهوا للعالم ،
Ling Wenyue's book,
كتاب لينغ وينيو ،
Study on the Yin Dynasty Calendar,
دراسة عن تقويم أسرة يين ،
tells the beginning of Chinese history.
يروي بداية التاريخ الصيني.
Impossible.
غير ممكن.
This is fake news.
هذه أخبار كاذبة.
Impossible!
غير ممكن!
This must be fake news!
يجب أن تكون هذه أخبار كاذبة!
This is fake news.
هذه أخبار كاذبة.
Fake news.
أخبار مزيفة.
It's here, hide.
إنه هنا ، اختبئ.
2127 will enter attack line.
2127 سيدخل خط الهجوم.
Two minutes left.
بقي دقيقتين.
The bomber gets ready to drop the bombs.
المفجر يستعد لإلقاء القنابل.
I'm ready to drop the bombs.
أنا مستعد لإلقاء القنابل.
One degree to the left.
درجة واحدة إلى اليسار.
The B-25 bomber is heading here.
قاذفة B-25 تتجه هنا.
B-25, Doolittle Raid.
ب 25 ، دوليتل ريد.
We were ambushed.
تعرضنا لكمين.
Break out of here!
اخرج من هنا!
Come on, Uncle Ling.
تعال ، العم لينغ.
Come on.
هيا.
I'll do it.
سأفعل ذلك.
The oracle bone of Wuding.
عظم الوضوء.
I'll get it, you can go down first.
سأفهم ، يمكنك النزول أولاً.
Wait, Haitang.
انتظر ، هايتانج.
It's not important.
انها ليست مهمة.
Humans can pass on the culture, not an oracle bone.
يمكن للبشر نقل الثقافة ، وليس عظام أوراكل.
Come on, let's go.
هيا بنا نذهب.
There is a sniper, don't come closer.
هناك قناص لا تقترب.
Fire!
نار!
One degree to the left, keep the height.
درجة واحدة إلى اليسار ، حافظ على الارتفاع.
Good condition for dropping bombs.
حالة جيدة لإلقاء القنابل.
Countdown 60 seconds.
عد تنازلي 60 ثانية.
Gao Lin, Gao Lin.
جاو لين ، جاو لين.
Gao Lin.
جاو لين.
Don't come here!
لا تأتي إلى هنا!
Don't come here.
لا تأتي إلى هنا.
There is a sniper on the mountain.
هناك قناص على الجبل.
Give me the lighter.
أعطني ولاعة.
Uncle Meng, don't go.
العم منغ ، لا تذهب.
You can't go.
لا يمكنك الذهاب.
Uncle Meng.
العم منغ.
Don't go.
لا تذهب.
Be careful.
كن حذرا.
Cunning Chinese.
الماكرة الصينية.
Bomb bay is open, ready to drop bombs.
خليج القنابل مفتوح وجاهز لإلقاء القنابل.
Waiting for order.
في انتظار الطلب.
Bomber...
قاذفة القنابل...
As pilots,
كطيارين ،
you should always keep an eye out for any useful information.
يجب أن تراقب دائمًا أي معلومات مفيدة.
Fire,
نار،
flicker,
رمش،
smoke,
دخان،
these could all be signals,
كل هذه يمكن أن تكون إشارات ،
and could be important messages someone is trying to convey to us.
ويمكن أن تكون رسائل مهمة يحاول شخص ما إيصالها إلينا.
It's easy to press the button to drop bombs.
من السهل الضغط على الزر لإلقاء القنابل.
But,
ولكن،
there are fathers and mothers,
هناك آباء وأمهات ،
brothers and sisters,
الاخوة والاخوات،
elders, women and children down there.
شيوخ ونساء وأطفال هناك.
There's a stop signal, stop dropping bombs.
هناك إشارة توقف ، توقف عن إلقاء القنابل.
2127 calling control tower.
2127 استدعاء برج المراقبة.
There is a triangle beacon signal.
هناك إشارة منارة مثلث.
It's an agreed signal of Hanguang Squadron,
إنها إشارة متفق عليها من سرب Hanguang ،
which means to stop dropping bombs.
وهو ما يعني التوقف عن إلقاء القنابل.
Please withdraw the order of dropping bombs.
يرجى سحب أمر إلقاء القنابل.
Control tower, control tower.
برج المراقبة ، برج المراقبة.
If we can't contact Wujiaba,
إذا لم نتمكن من الاتصال Wujiaba ،
we need to drop bombs as the order.
نحن بحاجة إلى إلقاء القنابل حسب الطلب.
Bomber, ready to drop bombs.
القاذفة جاهزة لإلقاء القنابل.
Wait.
انتظر.
I heard the sound of Xishan.
سمعت صوت شيشان.
Captain.
قائد المنتخب.
It's Captain.
إنه كابتن.
Captain!
قائد المنتخب!
You know my order.
أنت تعرف طلبي.
Stop dropping bombs.
توقفوا عن إلقاء القنابل.
What did he say?
ماذا قال؟
I can't hear it.
لا استطيع سماعه.
♫ A high wind is brewing. Ripping the thorns ♫
هناك رياح شديدة تختمر.  تمزيق الأشواك ♫
♫ Seize every day to seek justice ♫
اغتنم كل يوم لطلب العدالة
♫ Shed tears to our sweet love ♫
♫ تذرف الدموع على حبنا الحلو ♫
♫ The date of return is yet to come ♫
موعد العودة لم يأت بعد ♫
♫ The faith and zeal in heart ♫
v الإيمان والغيرة في القلب ♫
♫ Life and death hanging by a thread ♫
الحياة والموت معلقان بخيط ♫
♫ Sincerity blooms all over the land ♫
الإخلاص يزهر في جميع أنحاء الأرض ♫
♫ See the man of iron raise his gun ♫
شاهد الرجل الحديدي يرفع بندقيته
♫ The pursuit in the words of scholars ♫
السعي في كلام العلماء ♫
♫ Guard every inch of our territory with life ♫
♫ حماية كل شبر من أراضينا بالحياة
♫ Look back in the end. My love for my homeland stays ♫
♫ انظر إلى الوراء في النهاية.  حبي لوطني يبقى ♫
♫ The faith and zeal in heart ♫
v الإيمان والغيرة في القلب ♫
♫ Life and death hanging by a thread ♫
الحياة والموت معلقان بخيط ♫
♫ Sincerity blooms all over the land ♫
الإخلاص يزهر في جميع أنحاء الأرض ♫
♫ See the man of iron raise his gun ♫
شاهد الرجل الحديدي يرفع بندقيته
♫ The pursuit in the words of scholars ♫
السعي في كلام العلماء ♫
♫ Guard every inch of our territory with life ♫
♫ حماية كل شبر من أراضينا بالحياة
♫ Look back in the end. My love for my homeland stays ♫
♫ انظر إلى الوراء في النهاية.  حبي لوطني يبقى ♫